all right
[Music]
as the chair of Harvard's Nutrition
department put it transitioning Global
diets towards healthy plant-based
dietary patterns would require
large-scale Public Health efforts but
could be instrumental in ensuring future
human health
in my book how not to diet the chapter
on habit formation I talk about how you
can change your existing bad habits to
good ones or establish new good habits
from scratch using a technique known as
implementation intentions instead of
vague self-promises to do our best
implementation intentions are specific
if then plans to perform a particular
behavior in a specific context they take
the form of when situation X arises I
will perform response y for example if I
get hungry after dinner I will eat an
apple if the triggering circumstances of
regular daily occurrence implementation
intentions can be a beginning of a
beautiful habit so what about using
implementation intentions to cut down on
meat after all most food choices just
due to ingrained habits and meat is no
exception
here that we're trying to get people to
change from a climate perspective noting
more greenhouse gas emissions from
animal AG than all cars trucks trains
ships and planes combined but whatever
the reason researchers randomized people
to form if then plans for example if I
visit the University cafeteria for lunch
tomorrow then I will choose one of the
vegetarian meals motivated people to
consciously form an implementation
intention specifically how to implement
a goal seems to be such a simple
technique but it works forming an
implementation intention LED people not
only to think more often about their
intention to reduce meat consumption but
also to eat less meat despite the strong
force of habit on one hand breaking a
habit may be one of the most challenging
tasks we set ourselves on the other hand
a first yet effective step in getting
there seems to be writing down the goal
of change in the form of an if then
statement on a piece of paper
even a journey of a Thousand Miles
begins with a single step how else can
we transition to reduced meat diets we
talked about making the healthier option
the default option we could also
minimize disruption by producing
affordable recognizable and tasty
plant-based meat Alternatives the topic
of plant-based meat Alternatives has
been discussed for several decades but
it's only recently become one of the
hottest Topics in the food and research
communities after all one of the largest
perceived barriers for switching Dives
was the enjoyment of eating meat and so
if you can deliver a similar taste and
mouth feel it could help people shift
and it seems like it's working in recent
years in North America plant meat sales
grew by 37 percent I did a whole 12 part
video series on the human health
implications of various meat substitutes
but that was before this study came out
the study with appetizing plant food
meat eating alternative trial or Swap
Meet the company that makes the Beyond
Burger decided to put up or shut up by
funding a study through Chris Gardner's
prestigious Lab at Stanford a randomized
crossover trial to compare the effect of
consuming plant-based alternative meat
to animal meat on human health by having
people eat at least two surveys a day of
plant versus animal meat for eight weeks
each while keeping everything else as
similar as possible so instead of
burgers and beef from cows sausage from
pigs and breasts from chickens they ate
Burger sauces and chicken made from
Plants now if they're trying to game it
to give beyond meat an advantage they'd
have chosen the worst possible Meats to
compare it to but no the meats were
organic grass-fed to give the fairest
comparison possible so what happened
significant drop in tmao levels during
the plant-based meat phase that's a good
thing as I've explored before the
consumption of meat Dairy and eggs can
be turned by bad gut bacteria into
trimethylamine which is oxidized bar
liver into tmao which is associated with
heart failure kidney failure and our
number one killer atherosclerosis the
hardening of Our arteries
the plant-based meat group also achieved
a significant drop in cholesterol no
surprise given that lower saturated fat
intake of course if they had been eating
whole plant Foods instead like beans
saturated fat would have been way down
fiber way up and sodium way down in fact
there was basically no difference in
sodium intake so no surprise no
difference in blood pressure
the big surprise was weight during the
plant-based meat phase they
inadvertently lost a couple pounds some
of the plant-based meats are highly
processed and normally you'd expect
people to gain weight however weight was
modestly but statistically significantly
lower after eight weeks on the plant
rather than the animal phase notably
this was observed despite no differences
in reported total calorie integral or
physical activity levels between each
phase same calories yet less weight
we've seen this before same calorie
restriction yet more weight loss eating
more plant-based Slimmer waste less body
fat this may be from the fewer branched
chain amino acids and plant protein
compared to animal protein or because
the resting metabolic rate and those
eating vegetarian is as much as 20
percent higher so you're basically just
burning more calories in your sleep
please